Puerto Rican Civil Court Documents Collection 2000.0130
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Puerto Rican Civil Court Documents Collection
1844-1900.
2000.0130
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
5.2 Linear feet
Included are approx. 5000 documents dated between 1840s to the 1890s, many of which are from the Arecibo civil (corte de primera instancia) court districts, covering the full range of cases that might have been brought to civil courts in those times mainly disputes over economic holdings such as land disputes, sale of slaves, and similar materials. The collection includes court cases from the towns of Arecibo, Barceloneta, Camuy, Ciales, Hatillo, Manati, Morovis, Quebradillas, and Utuado.
Puerto Rican Insular Courts System
History
Puerto Rico was a colony of Spain for the period covered by most of the documents included in this collection (until the Spanish- American War of 1898). Under Spanish rule the civil courts of Puerto Rico fell under territorial jurisdiction. The island was divided into judicial districts corresponding to the major municipal areas (e.g., Aguadilla, Arecibo, Mayagüez.)
Scope and Content
The collection consists of court documents in manuscript hand. The materials span the dates 1844-1900, with the bulk of the collection dated between 1870-1890.
Arrangement
The records are arranged chronologically in one series.
Location of Copies or Alternate Formats
The Puerto Rican Civil Court Documents Collection was digitized thanks to a grant by the Center of Research Libraries' LAMP initiative, http://www.crl.edu/area-studies/lamp. The digital reproduction of this collection is available electronically at the Internet Archives at http://tinyurl.com/77uetxn.
Acquisition Information
The collection was purchased in 2000.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of published materials pertaining Puerto Rico and Latin America. See especially, the Puerto Rican collection of printed books, pamphlets, government documents, and periodicals on the social, economic, political, and literary history of Puerto Rico during the late 19th and early 20th century. The Spanish Periodicals Collection, which spans three centuries with the bulk of the materials covering the years 1800-1840, is abundant with information on all aspects of Spanish society: politics and government, history, literature, science, the arts, religion, and economy and trade with much detail also about life and society in the Spanish territories of Latin America and the Caribbean. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Courts--Puerto Rico.; Legal Records.; Puerto Rico--History to 1989--Sources.; Puerto Rico.
- Series I: Civil Court Documents, 1844-1900
  - 1844-1845 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - 1846-1847 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - 1852-1853 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - 1856-1857 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - 1858-1859 (Box 1:, Folder 5-11)
  - 1860-1861 (Box 1:, Folder 12-22)
  - 1862-1863 (Box 1:, Folder 23-28)
  - 1864-1865 (Box 1:, Folder 29-32)
  - 1866-1867 (Box 1:, Folder 33-34)
  - 1868 (Box 1:, Folder 35-39)
  - 1869 (Box 1:, Folder 40-42)
  - 1868-1869 (Box 1:, Folder 43)
  - 1870-1871 (Box 1:, Folder 44)
  - 1872-1873 (Box 1:, Folder 45)
  - 1874-1875 (Box 1:, Folder 46)
  - 1876-1877 (Box 1:, Folder 47-48)
  - 1878 (Box 1:, Folder 49-50)
  - 1878-1879 (Box 1:, Folder 51)
  - 1879 (Box 1:, Folder 52-64)
  - 1880 (Box 2:, Folder 1-13)
  - 1881 (Box 2:, Folder 14-21)
  - 1882-1883 (Box 2:, Folder 22-44)
  - 1882 (Box 2:, Folder 45)
  - 1883 (Box 2:, Folder 46)
  - 1884-1885 (Box 2:, Folder 47-57)
  - 1886 (Box 3:, Folder 1)
  - 1887 (Box 3:, Folder 2)
  - 1886-1887 (Box 3:, Folder 3-16)
  - 1888 (Box 3:, Folder 17)
  - 1889 (Box 3:, Folder 18)
  - 1888-1889 (Box 3:, Folder 19-31)
  - 1890-1891 (Box 3:, Folder 32-38)
  - 1892-1893 (Box 3:, Folder 39-60)
  - 1892-1893 (Box 4:, Folder 1-3)
  - 1894-1895 (Box 4:, Folder 4-31)
  - 1896-1897 (Box 4:, Folder 32-47)
  - 1898-1899 (Box 4:, Folder 48-50)
  - 1900 (Box 4:, Folder 51)